you
there's another way to look at
filmmaking which says that the Euler
characteristic of an older national
compact
without boundary manifold it's always
zero which is called Punk irregularity
it turns out that if you have the
composition of that manifold into a
network you know with vertices edges
faces blocks of various dimension
various cells you can it turns out
always draw an upside down Network what
I mean is let's take the
three-dimensional case that the edge the
up side network is for each vertex you
have a face and for each edge you have
another edge but in a perpendicular
direction and for each top face you have
a vertex and so this is called to
encourage relative or sometimes variety
simply and in fact the student
presentation first day which will show
you an example the most elementary
example historically the first example
of this variety but anyway using this
upside-down duality you can get this
result but that's maybe a discussion for
the next day's course okay that's a good
sampling of how to use the left-hand
side of one can I hope to get the
right-hand side I like to remind you the
topic of this film 15 from last time
next let's use this same powerful
theorem in the other direction we do
right hand side to the next and left
hand side in other words how the
knowledge of topology controls the
behavior of a dynamical system that
lives on that manifold okay if you know
something about topology of the
underlying space well a dynamical system
that lives on the space cannot behave in
an arbitrary fashion it has to have lots
and
constraints on its behavior here is
probably the most important result in
this direction
I shall stake it in a way that is
different from most trick metal
topologies that you find in text but I
think this is going to be the easiest
form to use suppose that you have a
vector field or a dynamical system on a
manifold vector field on a closed
orientable manifold sign at some finite
dimension then I am interested in the
number of equilibria of this vector
field you know you draw any vector field
we have for example drawn here two kinds
of vector field on the same manifold
Sigma G I can draw this kind of a few or
this vector field
okay and here and here the number of
equilibria was different yeah I forget
how many equilibria there were maybe
there are two plus two G
equilibria right total well two of them
had positive sign to G of them had
negative sign so the Euler turn this
cannot be this way here you had whatever
it is a lot of equilibria more than two
plus poochy so we see that in this case
there are fewer equilibria than indices
here for example the two equilibria but
can you draw a vector field with not to
Olivia on a sphere but only one
equilibrium or for that matter can you
draw a vector field that has no
agreement at all you can ask yourselves
that kind of question is the question
clear
so what is the minimum number of
equilibria that you must have because of
the topology the answer is very nice the
number of equilibria of this ugly vector
field must be bounded below by the Euler
characteristic but the absolute value of
the Euler characteristic this absolute
value is important for example in this
case of CQG usually this number is
negative
indeed for G started from two three four
five and so on it's all negative G
equals 1 it is 0 but I'm saying that you
can bound below the number of equilibria
by the absolute value of this so even if
it's a negative number the absolute
value is positive so this becomes a
strong bound if we had some negative
number mister then the bound is
completely trivial because Nana is of
course number Cleveland is always 0
positive and you can't have -2 no dress
it's good to note that only on this left
hand side
or equilibria when I say number Bolivia
they are all counted positive
you should them unlike when we are doing
the intersection theory for example when
we come to number B intersection points
or number equilibria like gamma zero
little circle gamma D where each
equilibrium is counted with positive or
negative sign so this is all positive
please be careful okay in particular
this is part of the theorem in
particular because of this inequality
every bit of you on s even must have a
vector field
I must have excuse me equilibrium must
have
a manifestation of what I was talking
about namely that the topology you know
of the manifold in captivity s even
constrains the behavior consistent on
that manifold you know that the Euler
characteristic class even is always - in
all even dimensions so that's greater
than equal to that means that there must
exist some equilibria
in fact number Bolivia is going to be at
least a little caveat caveat means
warning when we say equilibria we are
really talking about a generic picture
not a digital picture it turns out that
you can draw a vector field on s2 for
example s even there has only one
equilibrium not two but that's because
that one equilibrium turns out to be
degenerate and if you shake it a little
bit if you draw try to draw the picture
on the moving train if you move it into
transversality if you make the picture
generic you get to equilibrium
I shall show you such pictures on the
next program sheet but in the meantime
just solve the factor if you have
nonzero Euler characteristic your vector
field or your dynamical system must have
equilibrium in other words points where
you don't move stationary points okay
this left-hand side number of equilibria
okay that's right details number
equilibria can give ya is equal to I can
write it rather awkwardly like this
summation over all the equilibria my
doctor Phoebe but instead of summing
index at each point plus or minus one
I'm going some just some just plus one
okay for each equilibrium I just give
plus one that's going to give you the
number of equilibria of course but this
plus one can be interpreted as the
absolute value of the index of V at X
right because the index of V at X is
plus or minus one so if I could have
some value they all become plus one but
do you remember one can hope is that
some of the indices some of the index
equals the Euler characteristic so what
do you think if you have a plus B equals
let's see if I put an absolute value
everywhere what do you get you get a
greater than or equal to C do you
realize this in case B for example is
negative and n is positive C might end
up becoming smaller because of some
cancellation but this is saying I'm now
removing on the cancellations so the sum
of the absolute values is greater than
equal to the absolute value of the son
triangle inequality if you like so this
is a greater than equal to absolute
value of the sum which is simply by home
to interrupt the Euler characteristic
and of proof the firm that we have just
proved namely that on even damage those
fears in particular on s to every vector
field every field of arrows every line
field every field of directions on s to
every vector field must have an
equilibrium that theorem is sometimes
for the hairy ball theorem let me
explain why do you know what Harry means
somebody who has a lot of hair maybe who
has a lot of body hair that's Harry
Harry was here o impossibility combing
hedgehog do you know the hedgehog is a
resume in French but I will do a picture
so what would mean is a form suppose
that we have a sphere but which has a
lot of hair hair coming out from all
over the place
do you imagine such a thing or
directions and suppose that you want to
make all those hairs tangent to the
sphere can you do it in a smooth way in
a continuous very well the theorem is
that when whatever you do you must have
to end up with a place which looks like
for example a source or sink you cannot
have this sort of aligned picture
everywhere and the reason is you can
regard the this tangent picture whether
all the hair has been meant all the
heads of being made tangent as a picture
of a vector field and this theorem says
that because the oil o'clock three six
two non zero you have to have equilibria
those are points where you cannot have
this kind of picture a much better
representation might really like this
suppose that we have a hedgehog in case
you don't know what Hedgehog is in
English I'm sure you know yes this is
the head
do you recognize this animal yes so I
suppose this is a mathematical
idealization of the Hedgehog
okay it's not the real casual it's an
idealized headshot suppose that Hedgehog
has lots and lots of hair and you want
to comb it when you comb a hedgehog you
cannot calm it like this everywhere you
have to produce singularities like this
that's an interpretation of this theorem
Harry both you good understand the
theorem that we have just proved which
is really as I said a prototype of how
the topology constrains the behavior of
a dynamical system on that manifold
let's look at one or two examples by way
of a remark
like that okay so I see what's wrong
remark 20 we understand this theorem a
little better it can be shown although
we will not quite show it because it's
not difficult but it takes slightly long
discussion and unfortunately I'm not
here for a long time what about the
converse suppose that the Euler
characteristic is zero that means that
the number of equilibria of a vector
field is greater than or equal to zero
well that's obvious because number is
always positive but the question is is
this equal inequality sharp in other
words if the right-hand side becomes
zero can you make the left-hand side
zero also a greedy which it turns out
that the answer is yes then in this case
M admits as we say and everywhere
nonzero vector field in other words a
vector field has no equal
okay that is maybe this result it can be
shown that is also due to the same hope
of Portela hopes I think in the same
paper that he wrote in the 1920s let's
show this by some examples we already
know that people all that characteristic
of t2 is 0 which means that although
when we calculated the Euler
characteristic from that rainfall
picture we have the equilibria we should
be able to draw a gun encode system or
vector field on t2 two-dimensional torus
that has no equilibrium and that's
relatively easy imagine a torus necklace
and we shall consider the fine motion on
the torus I just keep going around
around with if you like uniform speed
uniform angular speed clearly this
vector field or dynamical system has
been no equilibrium he doesn't stop
anyway and it's a completely general
picture so there is no equilibrium the
number of equilibrium points is zero
that's okay
another possibility you might like to go
in this direction in the other circular
direction so I'm if you like going from
outside in
can you visualize this I have a Taurus
like this I'm just turning Taurus like
this kids under underneath he just keeps
going like this like this like this like
this and so and this vector field has no
equilibrium either oh these two pictures
although they look different are in fact
the same because think of the torus as
made from a square you remember how you
can make a torus I can identify this
edge with this edge and this edge with
this edge now that's what it is well
this vector field is simply a vector
field that goes this way and this vector
field is a vector field that goes this
way so either I'm rotating this like
this or rotating like this so it's the
same picture you don't have to draw this
picture I'll leave it anyway so you can
draw they exist I work with you know
equilibrium everywhere nonzero vector
field
how about odd dimensional sphere we also
know that the Euler characteristic is
zero according to this side remark I
hope we should be able to draw and every
non vanishing every nonzero vector see
you in the case of Islam it is extremely
easy to do so you should see this
yourselves this is a swamp and on this
one let's put it this one inside r2 as I
indicated you can just take a vector
field which is going around and round
like this it's a tangent that a field
which simply rotates the so that's one
and it's everyone on 0 of course you
don't have to stop ok
now let's write this in by formula so
what is V V of X y at the point X 5 what
is this how can I write this in at a
formal let's see we worked on this
example in the exercise session
yesterday do you remember what the
formula for huh - my ex exactly and it's
obvious because minus 1 X is equal to 0
minus 1 1 0 X Y what is this matrix
it's the rotation and by 90 degrees so I
take a radius vector at this point I
take this vector I rotated by 90 degrees
I'm going to get this vector ok so
that's obviously the case so this is a
formula our business now is to
generalize this to higher dimensional
spheres of all damage what happens on s3
for example three-dimensional cos 5 5
dimensional sphere and so in general
let's do it on as M minus 1 which is a
subset of r2 m Lima but if the sphere
has automation the ambient Euclidean
space in which the sphere seats has that
dimension plus 1 okay you can consider
the following vector field vector field
at the point instead of writing x1 x2
all the way to X 2m let me write the
coordinates in a funny notation x1 y1 x2
y2 all the way to X M Y M
okay how many codes are there two
importance so we shall denote the
coordinates on our 2m like this and the
vector field at each point is simply
going to be the generalization of the
one dimensional is maybe minus 1 Y 1 X 1
minus y 2 X 2 and so on going down to
minus PI M X M that's the vector field
on the sphere when we say it's a vector
field on the sphere we have to check
that this vector field is tangent to the
sphere but that's the same thing as
saying it's perpendicular to the radius
vector but it's obviously perpendicular
to the radius vector if you take a dot
product of this with the position vector
which is x1 y1 x2 and y2 and so on
it becomes 0 so it is tangent to the
sphere it was on s 2 n minus 1 this V is
everywhere perpendicular to
to the radius like that
so he keys everywhere tangent to the
sphere surface of the sphere okay
moreover in order to show that this is
the object we wanted in namely not only
a vector field on the automation of
sphere but it's everywhere nonzero
that's a mission we are saying that if
the electric field is zero we can always
construct that manifold always admits
and every unknown zero that the field
vector field with at equilibrium we have
to check that he has no agreement in
others he never becomes zero well you
might say wait a minute it becomes zero
at the origin ah but the origin is not
on the sphere so on the sphere this
vector fields every unknown 0 or s M to
M minus 1
because look at the magnitude of V V
squared it is equal to the sum over k k
from 1 to m of all these components
which is equal to minus 1 by K squared
plus XK squared but what is this well we
are on the sphere that is the sum of
these things must be equal to 1 and
that's nonzero ok
that's very okay that's more or less all
the time I wanted to convey to you today
I shall close with a remark or slightly
more advanced nature but which you
should be aware of in order to complete
the picture so that we have a more
honest picture of the subjects last
remark about this remark 21 you remember
that in all this discussion we are
visual trying to visualize the tangent
bundle and in what we call picture
number 6 a long time ago we visualized
the content control M which was a very
big and abstract object looking at n
cross R to M where m is damaged so
picture was we and then we somehow
imagine that you had a vertical
direction our M objective vector space
and then at each point of M we attached
tangent space which is essentially this
and we saw this kind of picture and this
kind of picture of course makes it look
like the tangent bundle looks like the
direct product of an M and all right but
this picture is correct only locally
they do exist cases in fact typically it
is the case that globally
this picture has direct products or
Cartesian product may be wrong let me
explain why can't go wrong
more precisely it is true that if you
find this a little hard or you can fall
asleep it's not going to matter it is
true that if you take a small
neighborhood you over that neighborhood
the path with the tangent bundle is a
direct product so for every small
neighborhood opens them
but not globally but it can happen that
all of Tanjung bando is not homomorphic
to the direct product with em together
with RF the next night this is in fact
very easy to understand why the tangent
mundo cannot usually be deterred product
the M and vector space you see indeed if
that's the case if the tangent were
always direct product then if that was
the case then we should always be able
to find an every unknown vanishing
vector field on all M contrary to our
discussion previously what I mean is if
you have this it's easy to write down
and every a constant vector field
P of X let's say let's say you have
those components would be every unknown
zero
you see everyone on 0 because the first
component is always wrong but by the
theorem that we have just proved through
we know that such vector field such a V
can exist only if the Euler
characteristic 0
and we know so that there are plenty of
money falls out there whose all a
characteristic is not zero so something
is going wrong and what is going wrong
is that in fact this tangent bundle
although we can't really draw the
picture and at this level some people in
fact it can be wrong in fact the country
model is usually twisted and I'd like to
mention that so that you might one day
remember this expression when you study
more advanced science that how twisted
degree or twisted nest in other words
how twisted TM is can be measured it
turns out by things objects called
characteristic classes this is one of
the main topics of topology as used by
physicists applied mathematicians and
also of course few mathematicians
scientists directors classes and we have
already seen a shadow over Chartist
class how something is twisted in fact
that all that artistic is precisely one
example of this whose most elementary
manifestation should I say shadow is the
Euler characteristic all that is rather
philosophical so let me give you a very
simple picture that conveys the flavor
of what I'm talking about let's say that
we take the ordinary strip untwist it
and consider the middle of this strip
okay
yeah things break okay so that's the new
middle of this trip and please imagine
that this middle strip is right with
zero section okay on this strip I can
draw a vector field so to speak which is
if you think of this as TM which is
everywhere non vanishing every nonzero
that is I can draw an entire circle
which does not intersect the middle line
that's very easy right I just draw this
line a little above and this circuit if
you like does not intersect the orange
line that's very easy the middle here is
an interesting thought let's take your
favorite objects the movie strip and
consider its middle line middle like
this question can you draw a curve that
goes all the way around on this movie
strip that does not intersect the middle
middle that's quite interesting here it
was so easy let's try that here you see
that start here for example and you know
very very naively I'm singing along and
I think it's going to be easy I come
around come around oh it's going to be
very easy it's going to be very easy and
then I come down and I find myself here
and I promised myself that I just go
around once you remember this is a big
likely picture of the section of a
vector field so in order to close I must
cross the middle section which means
that I cannot avoid having an
intersection and in the language of the
vector field
I must have I'm forced to have an
equally
okay so they're stations like this when
the tangent bundle is twisted as you can
see and although that language has to
gain rather metaphorical at this stage
there is a precise way of doing science
of twisting and how twisted tangent
bundle is and I am saying that twisted
Ness can be measured by those wonderful
and mathematical objects for the
characteristic classes whether